Finding Aid for Paul Showers Papers 1783-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Paul Showers Papers 1783-1999, 1870-1990
Showers, Paul.
2 oversize folders
2 linear feet (in 4 boxes)
Paul Cutler Showers was a journalist and freelance writer. His writing and editing days began through involvement with The Gargoyle and The Michigan Daily while attending the University of Michigan. Showers's papers document his lengthy journalism career through his writings, recollections, and correspondence regarding the Detroit Free Press, the U.S. Army's Yank Magazine, and the Sunday New York Times. Family history played an important role in his life and can be seen through his collection of family photographs, recollections, and stories. In his later years, Showers became a prominent children's author known internationally for his work with the "Read and Find Out" series of science books for beginning readers.
0387; Aa 2; Ac; UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The material was donated by Kate B. Showers (donor no. 8911 ) in December, 2002.
The collection is open for research except for one closed folder that will open January 1, 2020.
Paul Showers was born on April 12, 1910 in Sunnyside, Washington. His parents returned to their home in Michigan a few years after his birth. His parents studied music at Michigan Normal College (now Eastern Michigan University) and returned to continue their careers: Frank Showers was a music teacher and choir director while M. Ethelyne Showers was a concert vocalist.
After graduating high school, Paul attended the University of Michigan to study English and theater. He became involved with many campus activities including university theater productions and Michigamua. Paul also joined the staff of the Michigan Daily and the Gargoyle, becoming an editor for both. He also formed life-long friendships with fellow writers from these publications.
Graduation in 1931 led to small theater roles throughout Michigan. His unsteady income was supplemented by freelance writing. In particular, he became the crossword puzzle creator for Life. At the time, Life was a prominent humor magazine and Paul designed extra large, witty puzzles full of puns and word plays. His time with Life ended when Time purchased the magazine and altered its focus.
Paul's career as a copy editor "newspaper man" began in 1937 when he became a member of The Detroit News's copy staff. After a few years, he relocated to New York City to work with the New York Herald-Tribune. His time with the newspaper was cut short when he entered the U.S. Army in 1942. While in the military, he began working for the Army's publication for soldiers, Yank Magazine. His involvement took him to Japan near the end of the war to work for the Okinawa branch of Yank. Diaries and recollections from this time describe his reactions to Japanese culture and post-war devastation of Japan.
The end of the war brought Paul back to New York City where he began his career as a copy editor with the New York Times Sunday Department. He took on additional roles during his time with the paper including Travel Editor (1949-1961), editor of the Sunday Magazine (1961-1976), and writer of book reviews and "Times Talk" columns. Paul turned in his New York Times resignation on July 4, 1976, declaring his own independence from the newspaper life.
Paul Showers was fascinated by children's process of learning reading skills. His curiosity led him to write Find Out by Touching in 1961. The book engaged children through scientific questioning and activities that were applied to their everyday life. The success of the book led him to author over twenty additional children's titles for the science series "Let's Read and Find Out." Paul Showers's clear, straightforward, and often humorous text paired with vivid illustrations combined to create award-winning books. The Bentley Historical Library holds little manuscript material regarding his activities as a children's author. However, his books, research materials, notes, publisher correspondence, production processes, and children's fan mail are located within the Kerlan Collection of the Children's Literature Research Collections at the University of Minnesota.
Paul Showers studied his family and ancestors throughout his life. His research, correspondence, and recollections reveal his desire to learn about the roots of his family's conservative actions and beliefs. Paul rebelled against these constraints:
I have spent my life trying to free myself from the straightjacket of my childhood and adolescence. All other objectives have been secondary. But a life is not a solitary entity. It is only one segment of a continuity of genes with its inheritance of opinions and attitudes, ambitions and illusions that passes down from one generation to the next. (Paul Showers Papers, Box 1, Personal and Professional Papers - Biographical Material - Chronology and Memories)
His introspective struggles are evident within his journals and correspondence. Descriptions vary between poetic entries and frank recollections. These personal admissions describe the clash between modern life and values rooted in 19th century America.
The Paul Cutler Showers Papers document the life of a writer and editor, a University of Michigan alumni, an avid genealogist, a World War II veteran, and a prominent children's author.
The arrangement of the papers maintains their original order of four series including Correspondence, Family History, Personal and Professional Papers, and Visual Materials. These are in alphabetical order except for the Personal and Professional Papers series, which follows its original chronological organization according to Paul Showers's career. The papers contain very little information about his work as a children's non-fiction author. This portion of his papers are within the Kerlan Collection, which is part of the Children's Literature Research Collections at the University of Minnesota.
Subjects:
Showers, Paul.; Authors.; New York times.; Gargoyle.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; Yank.; World War, 1939-1945--Journalists.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Showers, Paul.; Almont (Mich.); Japan.; Michigamua.; New York times.; Showers family.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; Yank.
Contributors:
Brett, Dorothy, 1883-1977.; Bemelmans, Ludwig, 1898-1962.; Fisher, M. F. K. (Mary Frances Kennedy), 1908-1992; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977.; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977.
Genre/Form:
Albums.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence Series (1898-1999, 0.4 lin. ft.) contains letters between Paul Showers's and his relatives, friends, and prominent people. Correspondence between Paul Showers and his parents is especially rich with detail. Letters from Paul vividly describe his life, work, surroundings, and activities. His University of Michigan letters discuss early 1930s campus activities, theater productions, his studies, involvement with The Gargoyle, and his finances. Later correspondence describes life in Detroit and New York City including musical and theatrical productions, newspaper life, and the cities in general. His letters are descriptive and emotional, often filled with thoughtful self and family reflections.
  Family history was of particular interest to Paul Showers. His collection of letters from the Showers and Walker families document his quest to describe and explain his origins. He maintained many friendships throughout his life, documented by a number of correspondents within his papers. His work at the New York Times generated many admirers, whose letters of gratitude are located in the Prominent Individuals and Institutions folder. The folder contains letters from Dorothy Brett, Vladimir Nabokov, Frank Sullivan, M.F.K. Fisher, Leopold Stokowski, Edward Brecher, Bette-Jane Raphael, Emily Haan, Ludwig Bemelmans, and Vine Deloria, Jr.
  - Family
    - Ethelyne Showers's Friends to Paul Showers 1973-1977 (Box 1)
    - Frank Showers, to and from friends and employers 1898-1941 (Box 1)
    - Frank and Ethelyne Showers to Paul Showers 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    - Kate Showers (regarding Paul Showers' memory booklet) 1999 (Box 1)
    - Paul Showers to Parents (Frank and Ethelyne Showers) 1929-1950, 1952-1953, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Showers Family 1931-1978 (Box 1)
    - Ethelyne Walker to Frank Showers 1907-1909 (Box 1)
  - Friends
    - Edmund Antrobus 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    - Audrey Keller 1977 (Box 1)
    - Olive Lee circa 1945-1994 (Box 1)
    - Alan Handley undated (Box 1)
    - Edith Ligetti 1994 (Box 1)
    - Chick McCarthy 1980-1984 (Box 1)
    - Doris Rich 1978 (Box 1)
    - George Spater 1972-1984 (Box 1)
    - James and Norma Spinning 1950-1976 (Box 1)
    - Various Correspondents circa 1970s-1989 (Box 1)
    - John Willing 1980 (Box 1)
  - Prominent Individuals and Institutions 1962-1979 (Box 1)
- Family History
  Family History (1783-1979, 0.2 lin. ft.) was infused within all aspects of Paul Showers's life. This series includes resources for learning about his family, including notes, original documents, collected recollections, and research. Paul Showers used these materials and his memories to create several family biographies. Two versions within his papers include "Domestic Legends," a biography of his conflicted mother, and "Family Chronicle," a group of collected stories about his ancestors.
  - "Domestic Legends," unpublished recollections regarding Ethelyne Showers 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Family Bible, Martha Kelly and George McCrany (photocopies), dates recorded: 1783-1934 (Box 1)
  - "Family Chronicle," unpublished Kelly, Showers, and Walker family history undated (Box 1)
  - Frank and Ethelyne Showers
    - Birth Record and Death Certificate 1882-1979 (Box 1)
    - Diplomas 1897-1936 (Box 1)
      (in oversize folder Ac)
    - Programs and Clippings 1900-1945 (Box 1)
    - Recollections undated (Box 1)
  - Showers Family History undated (Box 1)
  - Sources and Notes undated (Box 1)
  - Sunnyside, Washington Material 1992 (Box 1)
  - Walker Family undated (Box 1)
- Personal and Professional Papers
  Paul Showers's Personal and Professional Papers document his life's activities and beliefs. This series is divided into subseries that are generally arranged chronologically.
  - Biographical Material
    The Biographical Material subseries contains biographies and recollections regarding Paul Showers. It also includes his diaries and journals, frankly describing his thoughts, activities, and recollections of his earlier years. His vital records include a birth certificate and marriage license.
    - Biographies 1989-1999 (Box 1)
    - Chronology and Memories undated (Box 1)
    - Journal 1983-1991 (Box 1)
      [RESTRICTED until January 1, 2020 ]
    - "Notes" (journal) 1941-1970 (Box 1)
    - Vital Records 1910-1948 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    The University of Michigan subseries contains documents from his years of attendance (early 1930s) as well as papers regarding friendships his cultivated while studying at the university. Paul Showers's papers include documents describing the Comedy Club, theater productions, Phi Kappa Phi, Sigma Delta Chi, Michigamua, the Michigan Union The Summer Daily and The Gargoyle. The subseries includes papers about Alan Handley, fellow Gargoyle staff member who later became a Hollywood producer. Handley's activities with the Dinah Shore Show and other productions are described in the unpublished manuscript, All that Jazz." Recollections about Robert LaBour and George Spater are also included.
    - Alan Handley
      - "All that Jazz," unpublished manuscript circa 1960s (Box 1)
      - Recollections 1990 (Box 1)
    - Robert LaBour 1993 (Box 1)
    - Papers and Newspaper Clippings 1930-1931 (Box 1)
    - George Spater 1984 (Box 1)
  - Theater
    Paul Showers filled his time after his university career with theater work. This subseries describes his teacher and mentor, Amy Loomis, including recollections and newspaper clippings. The subseries also includes programs for theatrical productions and newspaper clippings about the shows.
    - Amy Loomis circa 1950s-1990 (Box 1)
    - Programs 1926-1934 (Box 1)
  - United States Army
    The United States Army subseries includes composition books and notes regarding American military life at the end of World War II. The Ito Travel Notes folder is particularly noteworthy for views of post-war Japan. The subseries also contains his official army documents as well as materials for and about Yank Magazine.
    - Composition Book 1942-1945 (Box 1)
    - Military Documents 1942-1946 (Box 1)
    - Travel Notes, Ito, Japan 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    - Wallet Miscellanea 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    - War Years Notebook-and Afterwards circa 1940s (Box 1)
    - Yank
      - Fiftieth Anniversary 1992 (Box 1)
      - Okinawa Materials 1945 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Work
    The Newspaper Work subseries includes material from his time at the Detroit Free Press and the New York Times. "Free Press Days" is a narrative describing his earliest professional encounters with the journalism world. The bulk of the subseries contains documents and clippings regarding his New York Times career including the creation of the Sandbox group and his dissonance with Lester Markel, editor of the Sunday Section. This subseries also contains articles, columns, and reviews written by Paul Showers for the New York Times.
    - (Detroit) Free Press Days circa 1940s (Box 2)
    - Editorial Copy Comments undated (Box 2)
    - Editorial Structure 1974 (Box 2)
    - Lester Markel 1963-1977 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings circa 1970s (Box 2)
    - New York University Graduate School 1951-1952 (Box 2)
    - Sandbox Group 1967-1995 (Box 2)
    - Sherwin Smith undated (Box 2)
    - "Signals from the Butterfly," The New York Times Magazine Cover Story, July 27, 1975 (Box 2)
    - "Topics of the Times" and Book Reviews New York Times, 1962-1975 (Box 2)
      (see also oversized folder Ac)
  - Writings
    The Writings subseries contains miscellaneous manuscripts and published works by Paul Showers. It includes early works from school days up to his army years. Also of interest are his Life crossword puzzles, "A Bath with Sojin," a tale about an aging star at the end of World War II, and Bexley, a lengthy fictional monograph written in autobiographical form and based on his own family. This subseries also contains two autobiographies by Paul Showers.
    - Airplane Flights undated (Box 2)
    - Autobiography 1989 (Box 2)
    - "A Bath with Sojin," New Yorker, April 13, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Bexley, undated (Box 2)
    - Childhood Compositions circa 1925 (Box 2)
    - Composition Notebooks 1930- circa 1950 (Box 2)
    - Life Crossword Puzzles, 1935 (Box 2)
    - Outstanding Science Books for Children Award for Sleep is for Everyone, 1974 (Box 2)
    - "Paul Showers," Something about the Author Autobiography Series, Volume 7, 1989 (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials Section (1860-1991) contains photograph albums, loose photographs, a drawing, and one film. The 16mm film depicts a family reunion, most likely from the early 1930s. There are three photograph albums within the collection. Martha Kelly's Album is oversized with an ornate red velvet cover. It contains large images of the Kelly, Vandecar, Walker, Peck, and Smith families. The Kelly, Smith, and Vandecar Families Photograph Album is a smaller, blue book with images from around the 1870s. The Almont Album contains scenic postcards and snapshots of the Walker and Showers families, including early images of Paul Showers.
  The loose photographs mainly consist of family portraits. There are many images from both his mother's and father's families. There are also many portraits of Paul Showers from early childhood to late in life. Photographs in folders from Yank, New York Times, and (Detroit) Free Press show Paul Showers along with his colleagues and work environment. Also of note are the images of Okinawa taken during the final year of World War II.
  - Photo Albums (Box 3)
    - Martha Kelly's Album (Paul Showers's Great Grandmother) circa 1860 (Box 3)
    - Kelly, Smith, and Vandecar Families circa 1860 (Box 3)
    - Almont-The Old Farm circa 1900-1915 (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Family Members, Unidentified circa 1860-1950 (Box 4)
    - (Detroit) Free Press and Theater Groups circa 1930s (Box 4)
    - Amy Loomis circa 1950-1990 (Box 4)
    - New York Times
      - Sandbox Group, Sunday Section Staff circa 1970 (Box 4)
      - Paul Showers circa 1950s (Box 4)
      - "Times Talk" 1950 (Box 4)
    - Frank and Ethelyne Showers 1907-1950s (Box 4)
      (see also oversized folder UAm)
    - Paul Showers
      - Childhood 1910-1928 (Box 4)
      - University of Michigan 1928-1931 (Box 4)
      - Adult 1933- circa 1991 (Box 4)
    - Showers Family circa 1870-circa 1900 (Box 4)
    - Sojin circa 1927 (Box 4)
    - George Spater 1980 (Box 4)
    - Walker and Kelly Families circa 1870-circa 1900, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Yank
      - Okinawa circa 1942-1946 (Box 4)
      - Press Photographs circa 1942-1945 (Box 4)
      - Staff circa 1942-1945 (Box 4)
  - Other visuals
    - Prints of Scanned Photographs, Walker, Kelly, and Showers Families and Almont, Michigan (Box 4)
    - Drawing of Paul Showers undated (Box 4)
    - Film of Family Reunion, circa 1930s, 16 mm (Box 4)